Okay, cool. So in my part of the lecture, I'll cover three topics. I'll be first going
좋아. 그래서 제가 강의할 부분에서는 세 가지 주제를 다루겠습니다. 나 먼저 갈게
over positional encoding, which basically discusses how we can incorporate positional
위치 인코딩에 대해 기본적으로 위치 인코딩을 통합하는 방법을 논의합니다.
information into our word embeddings. And then I'll be going over attention inference
정보를 단어 임베딩에 추가합니다. 그런 다음 주의 추론에 대해 살펴보겠습니다.
acceleration, which is which are methods that combine attention matrices to accelerate
가속은 주의 매트릭스를 결합하여 가속하는 방법입니다.
attention at inference. And third, I will wear based attention acceleration methods.
추론에 주의를 기울이십시오. 셋째, 기반 주의력 가속 방법을 착용하겠습니다.
So let's get started with positional encoding. So before we talk about the mechanism, the
이제 위치 인코딩을 시작해 보겠습니다. 따라서 메커니즘에 대해 이야기하기 전에
first mechanism rope, let's let me talk about why we need positional encoding.
첫 번째 메커니즘 로프, 위치 인코딩이 필요한 이유에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
So suppose you have a transformer, you're feeding a sentence into transformers, and
변환기가 있고 변환기에 문장을 입력한다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
you have a lot of words. In particular, you have w1 to let's say wn. And the first thing
당신은 말이 많습니다. 특히, wn이라고 말하려면 w1이 있습니다. 그리고 가장 먼저
you do is you feed them through embedding layer. It's called that like, e or something.
당신은 임베딩 레이어를 통해 그것들을 공급하는 것입니다. e라고 부르죠.
And then you get vectors x1 to xn. These are the outputs of the embedding layer and
그런 다음 벡터 x1부터 xn까지를 얻습니다. 이는 임베딩 레이어의 출력입니다.
w1 to wn are just raw words. And you feed x1, xn, you combine them into this big matrix
w1 ~ wn은 단지 원시 단어입니다. 그리고 x1, xn을 입력하고 이를 큰 행렬로 결합합니다.
x. And you say, okay, for every xi, I want to get, I want to get matrix matrices q, k,
엑스. 그리고 당신은 말합니다. 모든 xi에 대해 나는 행렬 행렬 q, k를 얻고 싶습니다.
m, v. So the way that we do that is we have three matrices pq, pk, and pv. And then we
m, v. 그래서 우리가 하는 방법은 세 개의 행렬 pq, pk, pv를 갖는 것입니다. 그리고 우리는
do xpq equal to q. And then the same for k and v. And you can see what happens here
xpq를 q와 동일하게 하세요. 그리고 k와 v도 마찬가지입니다. 여기서 무슨 일이 일어나는지 볼 수 있습니다.
is that x1 will be, this is effectively doing, multiplying, this is effectively, this here
x1은 다음과 같습니다. 이것은 효과적으로 수행되고, 곱해지며, 이것은 효과적으로 여기에서 발생합니다.
is effectively saying x1 pq, xn pq. Because we first multiply x1 by the first column pq,
사실상 x1 pq, xn pq를 말하고 있습니다. 먼저 x1에 첫 번째 열 pq를 곱하기 때문에
and then the second entry will be also x1 multiplied by the second entry of pq, which
그러면 두 번째 항목도 pq의 두 번째 항목에 x1을 곱하게 됩니다.
is exactly what we're going to get here. But the point is throughout this entire process,
이것이 바로 우리가 여기서 얻으려는 것입니다. 하지만 요점은 이 전체 과정에 걸쳐,
the positional information is not encoded. Here in the embedding, the embedding function,
위치 정보는 인코딩되지 않습니다. 여기 임베딩에서는 임베딩 기능이,
it doesn't take the index wi, it doesn't take this i into any consideration. And here when
그것은 인덱스 wi를 취하지 않고, 이 i를 어떤 고려에도 취하지 않습니다. 그리고 여기서는 언제
we, when we map it to q, the pq, when we multiply the matrix pq with just the matrix multiplication,
우리가 그것을 q, 즉 pq에 매핑할 때, 행렬 곱셈만으로 행렬 pq를 곱할 때,
so it also doesn't take the information, the positional information of the particular word
따라서 특정 단어의 위치 정보인 정보도 가져오지 않습니다.
into account. And when we later on do q, q, k, t, and take the softmax of it, and multiply
계정에. 그리고 나중에 q, q, k, t를 수행하고 그것의 소프트맥스를 취하고 곱하면
v, you see, there's still nowhere do we consider the positional information. So, so in a way
v, 알다시피, 위치 정보를 고려할 곳은 아직 없습니다. 그러니까 어떤 면에서는 그렇죠
the positional information is lost, if we just do raw transformers and don't look at
원시 변환기만 수행하고 살펴보지 않으면 위치 정보가 손실됩니다.
the positional encoding at all. So that's why we need positional information. And originally
위치 인코딩이 전혀 없습니다. 그래서 위치정보가 필요한 것입니다. 그리고 원래는
in the attention is all you need paper, there were two, two ways to combat this problem.
주의를 기울이는 데는 종이가 필요합니다. 이 문제를 해결하는 데는 두 가지 방법이 있었습니다.
So one way is to use sine cosine functions. And then we basically what we do is we add,
그래서 한 가지 방법은 사인 코사인 함수를 사용하는 것입니다. 그런 다음 기본적으로 우리가 하는 일은 다음을 추가하는 것입니다.
we add to each of these x i's, some sine cosine values, I'll be going with this later,
우리는 이들 x i 각각에 사인 코사인 값을 추가합니다. 이에 대해서는 나중에 다루겠습니다.
just to just to give you a brief on the other approach that was covered in tension is all
긴장 속에 다루어졌던 다른 접근 방식에 대해 간략하게 설명하는 것만으로도 충분합니다.
you need. There were learned positional embeddings that we could apply to each of these words.
당신이 필요합니다. 이러한 각 단어에 적용할 수 있는 학습된 위치 임베딩이 있었습니다.
So to talk about the sine cosine, sine cosine functions first, basically what we do is before
사인 코사인에 대해 이야기하려면 먼저 사인 코사인 함수를 사용하세요. 기본적으로 우리가 하는 일은 이전에 하는 일입니다.
we apply, so here is basically, we just talked about except they wrote it in w multiply x
우리는 지원합니다. 기본적으로 w 곱하기 x에 썼다는 점을 제외하고는 방금 이야기했습니다.
i, I wrote w x times p, you know, q k v. So we do here is for each of the x i's, we multiply
i, 저는 wx 곱하기 p, qk v라고 썼습니다. 그래서 우리는 x i 각각에 대해 곱합니다.
we add a positional vector to it. And basically this positional vector i is going to be heavily
여기에 위치 벡터를 추가합니다. 그리고 기본적으로 이 위치 벡터 i는 매우 커질 것입니다.
dependent on what this i is. And see, this is the p i here. And at each position of x
내가 무엇인지에 따라 달라집니다. 그리고 보세요, 이것이 여기 파이입니다. 그리고 x의 각 위치에서
i. So suppose that x i is a small vector. At even indices, we add sine, okay, sine of
나. 따라서 xi가 작은 벡터라고 가정해 보겠습니다. 짝수 인덱스에서는 사인을 추가합니다.
i over one 10,000 to T over D. And at odd positions, we add sine of i over 10,000 to T, sorry,
i는 1보다 10,000이 넘고 T는 D보다 큽니다. 그리고 홀수 위치에서는 T에 10,000이 넘는 i의 사인을 추가합니다. 죄송합니다.
cosine over D. And i is the positional vector at i. So as you can see, this is p i will be heavily
D에 대한 코사인. 그리고 i는 i에서의 위치 벡터입니다. 보시다시피, 이것은 파이가 무거울 것입니다
dependent on what I is. And it's going to be unique to the specific i. And T here is the index
내가 무엇인지에 따라. 그리고 그것은 특정 i에 고유할 것입니다. 그리고 T는 여기 인덱스입니다
within the, within p i, because p i is not a single value, it's an entire vector. So, you know,
pi 내에서 pi는 단일 값이 아니기 때문에 전체 벡터입니다. 아시다시피,
here T will be equal to one, here T will be two, and it's going to increase as we go along. So it's
여기서 T는 1이 될 것이고, 여기서 T는 2가 될 것이며, 계속해서 증가할 것입니다. 그래서 그것은
basically p i is going to be a unique combination of these sine and cosine values. And altogether,
기본적으로 파이는 사인과 코사인 값의 고유한 조합이 될 것입니다. 그리고 전체적으로,
they're supposed to transmit a unique signal. This vector is supposed to transmit a unique
그들은 고유한 신호를 전송해야 합니다. 이 벡터는 고유한 정보를 전송해야 합니다.
signal, depending on what this i is. So by adding this positional vector to x i, well, our goal is
이 i가 무엇인지에 따라 신호가 전달됩니다. 따라서 이 위치 벡터를 xi에 추가함으로써 우리의 목표는 다음과 같습니다.
to retain some information. Now, before we feed it into the attention part, we want to add some
일부 정보를 유지하기 위해. 이제 어텐션 부분에 입력하기 전에 몇 가지를 추가하고 싶습니다.
signal so that the attention part can know that, hey, this is maybe the i-th position, because
주의 부분이 알 수 있도록 신호를 보내세요. 여기가 아마도 i번째 위치일지도 모르니까요.
we've detected some, detected some signal here with the addition of p i. And there's been an
우리는 p i를 추가하여 일부 신호를 감지했습니다. 그리고 이런 일이 있었습니다.
ablation study that has shown that we can actually learn, based on the positional encoding,
위치 인코딩을 기반으로 실제로 학습할 수 있음을 보여준 절제 연구는
the absolute position of the, of the, of the basically, basically we can, we know that given
기본적으로 기본적으로 우리는 할 수 있다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
x i plus p i, we can learn i with a linear, linear regression.
xi에 pi를 더하면 선형 선형 회귀를 통해 i를 학습할 수 있습니다.
So basically, this is why we kind of need, we need a positional encoding in the first place.
기본적으로 이것이 우리에게 필요한 이유입니다. 우선 위치 인코딩이 필요합니다.
Okay, so how does rope encode the positional encoding? So I'm just going to bring you back
좋아요, 그렇다면 로프는 위치 인코딩을 어떻게 인코딩하나요? 그래서 난 그냥 당신을 다시 데려오려고 해요
to here. So we don't necessarily have to encode the positional information at the
여기로. 따라서 위치 정보를 반드시 인코딩할 필요는 없습니다.
signing soil stage. Consider the following setup. So we have w i, passes goes through an encoding,
토양 단계에 서명합니다. 다음 설정을 고려하십시오. Wi가 있고, 패스는 인코딩을 거치며,
becomes x, and then it goes through these projection matrices, and it becomes q k and v.
x가 되고 이 투영 행렬을 거치면 qk와 v가 됩니다.
And what we can do is that we're going to say we believe that for, for q and k,
그리고 우리가 할 수 있는 것은 우리가 q와 k에 대해 다음을 믿는다고 말하는 것입니다.
here, here, like each entry, the i-jth entry of this matrix is q i t k j. We're going to say
여기, 여기, 각 항목과 마찬가지로 이 행렬의 i-j번째 항목은 qitk j입니다. 우리는 말할 것이다
for for i and j that are far apart, then this signal doesn't matter so much.
멀리 떨어져 있는 i와 j의 경우 이 신호는 그다지 중요하지 않습니다.
Um, before i and j that are close, this signal is going to matter a lot. And then we want to,
음, 가까운 i와 j 이전에 이 신호가 많이 중요할 것 같아요. 그리고 우리는
we want to kind of convey this relative position information into, into the transformers.
우리는 이 상대적인 위치 정보를 변환기로 전달하고 싶습니다.
So, yeah, so that's the idea. So, so, so the way that rope does it is that
그래, 그게 아이디어야. 그래서, 그래서, 밧줄이 하는 방식은 다음과 같습니다.
basically the idea comes from in the complex plane. In the complex plane, if you want to rotate
기본적으로 아이디어는 복잡한 평면에서 나옵니다. 복소 평면에서 회전하려는 경우
a vector x by theta, you multiply it by e to the i theta.
벡터 x x 세타에 e를 i 세타로 곱합니다.
So here we say, in ropey say, if we want to rotate it, for x m, we rotate x m by m theta.
그래서 여기서 우리는 xm을 회전시키고 싶다면 xm을 m theta만큼 회전시킨다고 말합니다.
And we rotate x n by m theta. So as you can see, if, if x m and x n, which are assumed to be in the,
그리고 xn을 mθ만큼 회전시킵니다. 보시다시피, 만약에 가정된 xm과 xn이,
roughly the same area that they're being mapped to by the, by the, by the, by the word embedding
임베딩이라는 단어로 매핑되는 영역과 거의 동일합니다.
here, suppose that maps to like a particular area, that's, that's rather a small part of the whole
여기서는 특정 지역을 좋아하는 것으로 매핑된다고 가정합니다. 즉, 전체의 작은 부분에 해당합니다.
in higher dimension. Um, if m and n are close, then they're rotated to roughly the same area.
더 높은 차원에서. 음, m과 n이 가까우면 대략 같은 영역으로 회전됩니다.
But if m and n are far apart, then, then they're also going to be far apart. And what that really
하지만 m과 n이 멀리 떨어져 있다면, m과 n도 멀리 떨어져 있을 것입니다. 그리고 그게 정말 뭐야?
means is that, uh, here, here we're really not rotating x m anymore. We're rotating like q m and
즉, 어, 여기, 여기서는 더 이상 xm을 회전하지 않는다는 뜻입니다. 우리는 qm처럼 회전하고 있고
you know, q n and then k m and then k n. What, what this means is that when we take the dot product
qn, km, kn이 있죠. 이것이 의미하는 바는 우리가 내적을 취하면
here, the dot product is basically going to be small. Um, because we call that the dot product,
여기서 내적은 기본적으로 작을 것입니다. 음, 우리는 그것을 내적이라고 부르기 때문에
it's going to be basically, it's going to be, okay, maybe this is not the right symbol, but
기본적으로는 이렇게 될 것입니다. 알겠습니다. 어쩌면 이것은 올바른 기호가 아닐 수도 있지만
basically it has a term of, it's equal to q i k j multiplied by the, the cos of the angle between
기본적으로 그것은 qikj에 the를 곱한 것과 같습니다. 사이 각도의 cos입니다.
them. So if this is rotated by m theta, um, and this is rotated by n theta, then some of this,
그들을. 그래서 이것이 m 세타만큼 회전한다면, 음, 그리고 이것이 n 세타만큼 회전한다면, 이것 중 일부는,
the cos, the theta here is going to be something like m theta minus n theta, plus, plus some,
cos, theta는 m theta - n theta, plus, plus some과 같은 것이 될 것입니다.
some like smaller value. Um, so if m minus n is large, that means the theta is going to be large.
일부는 더 작은 값을 좋아합니다. 음, m 빼기 n이 크면 세타가 커진다는 의미입니다.
So then the cosine value is going to be small. Um, so then the signal won't, won't be as big.
그러면 코사인 값은 작아질 것입니다. 음, 그렇다면 신호는 그리 크지 않을 것입니다.
But if m and n are close, then the value, this dot product is going to be large. So that's,
그러나 m과 n이 가까우면 이 내적의 값은 커질 것입니다. 그래서 그건,
that's a way of telling the transformers to, to keep the product product large, if i and j are
이는 i와 j가 다음과 같은 경우 제품의 크기를 크게 유지하도록 변환기에 지시하는 방법입니다.
close. Um, but keep them small when they're far, far further apart. Uh, and the way we do that in
닫다. 음, 하지만 멀리 떨어져 있을 때는 작게 유지하세요. 어, 그리고 우리가 그렇게 하는 방식은
the complex plane is multiplying by e to the i of m theta. But if we consider, if we consider, uh,
복소 평면은 m θ의 i에 e를 곱합니다. 하지만 생각해 보면, 생각해 보면, 어,
if we consider this, the complex plane to be a bijection to the, to the r2 plane, um,
우리가 이것을 고려한다면, 복소 평면은 r2 평면에 대한 전단사(bijection)가 될 것입니다. 음,
okay, first of all, e to the i, e to the i m theta is equal to cos of
좋아요, 우선, e의 i, e의 im 세타는 cos와 같습니다.
m theta plus i sine of m theta. And then if we take this to be one coordinate, and we take this
m 세타 더하기 i 사인은 m 세타입니다. 그리고 이것을 하나의 좌표로 삼고 이것을 취하면
to be the other coordinate, this is the imaginary coordinate, and this is the real coordinate.
다른 좌표가 되려면 이것이 가상 좌표이고 이것이 실제 좌표입니다.
Um, and we multiply it to some, some, some arbitrary number.
음, 그리고 우리는 그것을 어떤 임의의 숫자에 곱합니다.
We'll basically get that multiplying by this, by this number to this is multiplying by, uh,
기본적으로 이것을 곱하면 이 숫자에 이 숫자를 곱하면, 어,
by a matrix to this. And that matrix is exactly this here. So basically we successfully math this
이것에 대한 매트릭스로. 그리고 그 행렬은 바로 여기에 있습니다. 기본적으로 우리는 이것을 성공적으로 계산합니다.
from, uh, from, from c to r, r2. And the way that we rotate a vector in r2 is basically just
에서, 어, 에서, c에서 r, r2. 그리고 r2에서 벡터를 회전하는 방식은 기본적으로
multiplying by this matrix here. And, um, I won't go into more details about this. And if we want
여기 이 행렬을 곱하면 됩니다. 그리고 음, 이것에 대해서는 더 자세히 설명하지 않겠습니다. 그리고 우리가 원한다면
to do this in higher dimensional, say, d dimensional space, um, what these guys propose is very
더 높은 차원, 예를 들어 d차원 공간에서 이 작업을 수행하려면 음, 이 사람들이 제안하는 것은 매우
simple. So suppose that we have, uh, this vector here, this is basically either q m or k m.
단순한. 그래서 우리가 여기에 이 ​​벡터를 가지고 있다고 가정해 보세요. 이것은 기본적으로 qm 또는 km입니다.
And it looks something like this. We say that we, we take every pair of coordinates and we
그리고 그것은 다음과 같습니다. 우리는 모든 좌표를 취하고 우리는
rotate the first pair by m theta one, rotate the second pair by m theta two, and so on and so forth.
첫 번째 쌍을 m 세타 1만큼 회전하고, 두 번째 쌍을 m 세타 2만큼 회전하는 식으로 계속됩니다.
And, and by the way, we keep, we keep the theta i's to be this, which are relatively smaller
그런데, 우리는 상대적으로 더 작은 세타 i를 이렇게 유지합니다.
numbers. Um, they're smaller. So, so to ensure that we don't rotate a full cycle. So basically if m and
숫자. 음, 더 작네요. 따라서 전체 사이클을 회전하지 않도록 보장합니다. 따라서 기본적으로 m과
n are, if m and n are actually far enough, m minus n times theta i, you know, it's equal to like,
n은, 만약 m과 n이 실제로 충분히 멀다면, m 빼기 n 곱하기 세타 i는, 아시다시피, 그것은 다음과 같습니다.
like two pi or something. So then it actually means that m and n are like kind of close. So we don't,
2 파이 같은 거요. 그렇다면 그것은 실제로 m과 n이 일종의 가깝다는 것을 의미합니다. 그래서 우리는 하지 않습니다.
we don't want that to happen. So to keep, so we keep it small. Um, and yeah, so this is what I
우리는 그런 일이 일어나기를 원하지 않습니다. 그래서 우리는 그것을 작게 유지합니다. 음, 그리고 그래, 그래서 내가 하는 말이야
talked about, um, keeping the, basically want to apply the positional encoding at, during the,
음, 기본적으로 위치 인코딩을 적용하려고 하는 동안에 대해 이야기했는데,
uh, during the matrix multiplication between q and k. And this is q. This is k.
어, q와 k 사이의 행렬 곱셈 중에요. 그리고 이것은 q입니다. 이것은 k입니다.
This is basically q m. This is k n. And we rotated this by n theta and this m theta. And,
이것은 기본적으로 qm입니다. 이것은 kn입니다. 그리고 우리는 이것을 n 세타만큼 회전시켰고 이것은 m 세타만큼 회전시켰습니다. 그리고,
you know, that's basically equivalent, uh, to multiplying by this matrix,
아시다시피, 이는 기본적으로 이 행렬을 곱하는 것과 동일합니다.
um, here. If we take the transpose of everything, basically what we can do is multiply these two
음, 여기요. 모든 것을 전치하면 기본적으로 우리가 할 수 있는 일은 이 두 가지를 곱하는 것입니다.
first, uh, which look like this. And when you multiply this by the transpose of the other one,
먼저, 어, 이건 이렇게 생겼어요. 그리고 이것을 다른 것의 전치와 곱하면,
which is going to be the negative theta, you're going to get m minus m theta.
이것은 음의 세타가 될 것입니다. 여러분은 m - m 세타를 얻게 될 것입니다.
And we can actually do the, the m minus m theta very fast. So we don't actually have to multiply,
그리고 우리는 실제로 m 빼기 m 세타를 아주 빠르게 할 수 있습니다. 따라서 실제로 곱할 필요는 없습니다.
this huge matrix right here by another huge one. Um, we can instead do this quick operation here.
이 거대한 행렬은 바로 여기 또 다른 거대한 행렬입니다. 음, 대신 여기서 빠른 작업을 수행할 수 있습니다.
And we can continue doing this for linear attention because common choices of them,
그리고 우리는 선형적 관심을 위해 이것을 계속할 수 있습니다. 왜냐하면 공통된 선택이 있기 때문입니다.
of the map here, um, basically, it's basically just like a normalization scheme.
여기 지도는 음, 기본적으로 정규화 방식과 같습니다.
So, like, they're still around. So this is like q and k. And then this is like v of
그래서, 그들은 아직 주변에 있어요. 그래서 이것은 q와 k와 같습니다. 그리고 이것은 v of
q and v of k. Like, they're still around the same area, um, after a normalization scheme.
k의 q와 v. 예를 들어, 그들은 정규화 계획 이후에도 여전히 같은 영역에 있습니다.
So rotating them, I guess the idea is that rotating, um, would still work.
그래서 그것들을 회전시키는 것은, 음, 회전하는 것이 여전히 작동할 것이라는 생각인 것 같아요.
Okay. So another, another thing to note is that
좋아요. 또 한 가지 주목해야 할 점은
sinusoidal encoding is applied at the very beginning. So applied
정현파 인코딩은 맨 처음에 적용됩니다. 그래서 적용
right here, when the word is mapped to embedding, we add, uh, here we add like a positional encoding
바로 여기, 단어가 임베딩에 매핑되면, 어, 여기에 위치 인코딩처럼 추가합니다.
PI. Yeah, like here. And it's only applied once throughout the entire transformers and
피. 응, 여기처럼. 그리고 이는 전체 변압기에 걸쳐 한 번만 적용되며
architecture. However, for rope, it is applied at every q and k. Every time you multiply,
건축학. 그러나 로프의 경우 q와 k마다 적용된다. 곱할 때마다,
you do this, you apply rope. Um, and yeah, this is like a bound on basically saying that, uh,
이렇게 하면 로프를 적용하게 됩니다. 음, 그리고 그래, 이건 기본적으로 이렇게 말하는 게 한계인 것 같아, 어,
if, if you have two things that are far apart, um, this is the relative distance. So this is
만약, 멀리 떨어져 있는 두 가지가 있다면, 음, 이것이 상대적인 거리입니다. 그래서 이것은
basically m minus m. This is the, the upper bound, um, and, uh, the upper bound, upper bound of
기본적으로 m 빼기 m입니다. 이것은 상한, 음, 그리고 어, 상한, 상한입니다.
how, um, how large their dot products between the rotated, rotated q and m and
음, 회전된 q와 m 사이의 내적은 얼마나 큰가요?
are, uh, yeah, this multiplied by q and m and then multiplied by, uh, the rotated k and how far,
어, 예, 이것을 q와 m으로 곱한 다음, 어, 회전된 k를 곱하고 얼마나 멀리 있는지,
okay, and there's nothing here. So basically how, how far these could be.
알겠습니다. 그리고 여기에는 아무것도 없습니다. 기본적으로 이것이 얼마나, 얼마나 멀리 있을 수 있는지.
And it's saying basically when, when, when n minus m is large and they're far apart,
그리고 그것은 기본적으로 언제, 언제, n 마이너스 m이 크고 서로 멀리 떨어져 있는지를 말합니다.
this value, this bound goes down, which is kind of what we want. Um,
이 값, 이 경계는 내려갑니다. 이것이 바로 우리가 원하는 것입니다. 음,
so here is how rope performs. So as you can see here on the, on this task over here,
로프의 성능은 다음과 같습니다. 여기에서 볼 수 있듯이 여기 이 작업에 대해
it does a bit better. Um, and on, on, on these tasks, on these downstream tasks,
조금 더 나아졌습니다. 음, 계속해서, 이러한 작업에 대해, 이러한 다운스트림 작업에 대해,
it performs better for some of them.
일부에서는 더 나은 성능을 발휘합니다.
Um, and for the mask lm scores, um, basically, uh, roll former, which the blue line is lower.
음, 그리고 마스크 영화 점수의 경우 음, 기본적으로 롤 포머인데 파란색 선이 더 낮습니다.
Same for lm here. This is masked. This is just normal lm and it's used by gb3.
여기 영화도 마찬가지야. 이것은 마스크되어 있습니다. 이것은 단지 일반적인 lm이며 gb3에서 사용됩니다.
Okay. So let's, that was a very fancy mechanism. And, um, let's look like, look at the next
좋아요. 자, 그것은 매우 멋진 메커니즘이었습니다. 그리고, 음, 다음을 봅시다
mechanism, which, which is called alibi. And it's much simpler compared to the previous one.
이를 알리바이라고 합니다. 그리고 이전에 비해 훨씬 간단해졌습니다.
And, um, the, the motivation for alibi is that, uh, models can take arbitrary long
그리고, 음, 알리바이의 동기는, 음, 모델이 임의로 오랜 시간이 걸릴 수 있다는 것입니다.
input lengths. Transformers models can take arbitrary long input lengths compared to what
입력 길이. Transformers 모델은 무엇에 비해 임의의 긴 입력 길이를 사용할 수 있습니다.
it has seen during your training. Um, so again, if you recall, what transformers does is basically
훈련 중에 본 적이 있습니다. 음, 다시 말씀드리지만, 트랜스포머가 하는 일은 기본적으로
it multiplies this x, which is your, uh, your embeddings that came from words.
그것은 이 x를 곱하는데, 이것은 여러분의, 어, 단어에서 나온 임베딩입니다.
Um, and there's, suppose there's n words and suppose the dimension of each of them is d,
음, 그리고 n개의 단어가 있고 각 단어의 차원이 d라고 가정해 보겠습니다.
and during, when, when you projected to matrix q, it multiplies x with the matrix q, which is,
그리고 도중에 행렬 q에 투영하면 x와 행렬 q를 곱합니다. 즉,
um, which is of dimension
음, 그건 차원이잖아
here, d times dq.
여기서는 d 곱하기 dq입니다.
So, so therefore how, how, however large n is, we can always multiply these two matrices together
따라서 n이 아무리 크더라도 우리는 항상 이 두 행렬을 곱할 수 있습니다.
and transformers will also always work. The thing is when we train on shorter lengths,
변압기도 항상 작동합니다. 문제는 우리가 더 짧은 길이로 훈련할 때,
length x's, it's usually unable to generalize well to longer length x's, x's, um, at inference time.
길이 x, 추론 시에는 일반적으로 더 긴 길이의 x, x, 음으로 일반화할 수 없습니다.
So alibi overcomes this and it's able to extrapolate to longer sequence lengths.
따라서 알리바이는 이를 극복하고 더 긴 시퀀스 길이로 추정할 수 있습니다.
And again, we've considered sinusoidal, which is intentionally all you need, rope, we just covered
그리고 다시 말하지만, 우리는 의도적으로 필요한 전부인 사인곡선을 고려했습니다. 로프는 방금 다루었습니다.
this and, uh, and there's also another learned embedding called t5 bias. Um, and the idea is that,
그리고 t5 편향이라는 또 다른 학습된 임베딩도 있습니다. 음, 그리고 아이디어는,
you know, sinusoidal is the worst and then rope and it's t5 bias, but alibi is still better. Um,
알다시피, 정현파는 최악이고 그 다음은 로프이고 t5 편향이지만 알리바이는 여전히 더 좋습니다. 음,
and another idea is that we might want to compute how, we don't want to compute the exact contact
또 다른 아이디어는 정확한 접촉을 계산하는 것이 아니라 어떻게 계산해야 하는지를 계산한다는 것입니다.
length that was fed in. Like another argument is that this might not be a fair comparison.
입력된 길이입니다. 또 다른 주장과 마찬가지로 이것이 공정한 비교가 아닐 수도 있다는 것입니다.
And what is actually fair is if we consider the amount of compute it takes, because sinusoidal
실제로 공평한 것은 필요한 계산량을 고려하는 것입니다.
is much lighter. So for example, um, for sinusoidal, maybe training like the length of 1024 is same
훨씬 가볍습니다. 예를 들어, 음, 정현파의 경우 1024 길이와 같은 훈련은 동일할 수 있습니다.
as training at the same transformers with the t5 bias, uh, with, with like context length 512.
t5 바이어스, 어, 비슷한 컨텍스트 길이 512를 사용하여 동일한 변환기에서 훈련하는 것입니다.
Um, because t5 bias takes a more compute, so training this and training this actually takes
음, t5 편향에는 더 많은 계산이 필요하기 때문에 이를 훈련하고 실제로 훈련하는 데에는
around the same compute. So what alibi does is it basically adds, so for, so for query i,
같은 계산 주위에. 따라서 알리바이가 하는 일은 기본적으로 추가하는 것입니다. 따라서 쿼리 i에 대해
it adds, um, query i dotted k is like you have one q here.
음, 내가 k로 점을 찍은 쿼리는 여기에 하나의 q가 있는 것과 같습니다.
And you have like a huge k matrix. You do this, multiply by this, you get like this value here
그리고 당신은 거대한 k 행렬을 가지고 있습니다. 이렇게 하고 이것을 곱하면 여기 이 값이 나옵니다.
and then you get this multiply by this and you get this value here. Um, and basically at this
그리고 이것을 곱하면 여기서 이 값을 얻게 됩니다. 음, 그리고 기본적으로는 이렇습니다
position here is the ith out of like many. Um, here we add minus i minus one. Here we add minus
여기 위치는 많은 것 중에서 i번째입니다. 음, 여기에 마이너스 i 마이너스 1을 더합니다. 여기에 마이너스를 추가해보겠습니다.
i minus two all the way to zero. And then zero is after that. Um, yeah, the reason that we, we,
나는 2를 빼고 0까지 갑니다. 그리고 그 이후에는 0이 됩니다. 음, 그래, 우리가, 우리가,
we add this is, um, for the same reason as before. For q, for q, for i and j,
우리는 이것이 음, 이전과 같은 이유라고 덧붙입니다. q에 대해, q에 대해, i와 j에 대해,
j is the same like the k index. For i and j that are far apart, we want the qi, qi dot k, we want qi
j는 k 인덱스와 동일합니다. 멀리 떨어져 있는 i와 j에 대해 우리는 qi, qi dot k, 우리는 qi를 원합니다
kjt. We want this value to be relatively smaller signal to our transformers model.
kjt. 우리는 이 값이 변압기 모델에 대해 상대적으로 작은 신호가 되기를 원합니다.
Um, it's in a way it doesn't matter as much. Um, and the, the reason that we have zeros all after
음, 어떻게 보면 별로 중요하지 않은 것 같아요. 음, 그리고 결국 우리가 0을 갖게 된 이유는
that is because, um, we want to add a mask so that the transformer doesn't cheat during training.
그 이유는 음, 훈련 중에 변환기가 부정 행위를 하지 않도록 마스크를 추가하고 싶기 때문입니다.
So basically, um, we have like, we have like, uh, what do we have? We have like my name
기본적으로, 음, 우리는 다음과 같은 것을 가지고 있습니다. 어, 우리는 무엇을 가지고 있습니까? 우리는 내 이름과 같은 것을 가지고 있습니다
is Matt. And during training, the q is going to, the first q is going to be like on my,
매트예요. 그리고 훈련 중에 q는 첫 번째 q가 내 것과 같을 것입니다.
and if we're trying to do language modeling, k is also going to be on my, and then, um,
그리고 우리가 언어 모델링을 하려고 한다면 k도 my에 있을 것이고, 음,
so that's going to be like the first one. And then, and then, and then q is going to have,
그래서 그것은 첫 번째 것과 같을 것입니다. 그리고 나서, 그리고 나서, 그리고 나서 q는,
um, basically my, this is basically, uh, wq times x1 equal to q1.
음, 기본적으로 내, 이것은 기본적으로, 어, wq 곱하기 x1 = q1입니다.
And then we're going to have, and then we're going to have, sorry, this is not,
그런 다음 우리는 다음을 갖게 될 것입니다. 죄송합니다. 이건 아닙니다.
and then we're going to have,
그런 다음 우리는
name is equal to like x2. So we're going to have, we're going to get q2 here. And
이름은 x2와 같습니다. 그래서 우리는 여기서 q2를 얻게 될 것입니다. 그리고
the idea is that when we're doing q1 times kt, um, we don't want to be able to get k2,
아이디어는 우리가 q1 곱하기 kt를 할 때, 음, 우리는 k2를 얻을 수 있기를 원하지 않는다는 것입니다.
which tells us about name, because this is equal to
이는 이름에 대해 알려줍니다. 왜냐하면 이것은 다음과 같기 때문입니다.
wq, wk times x2, and x2 is based on name. So, so we basically, if we're trying to complete,
wq, wk x x2, x2는 이름을 기준으로 합니다. 따라서 기본적으로 우리가 완료하려고 하면
we're trying to complete the sentence qi, like if we're trying to complete the sentence my,
우리는 qi 문장을 완성하려고 합니다. 마치 my라는 문장을 완성하려고 하는 것처럼,
we don't want k, k2, it already tell you what the next word name is.
우리는 k, k2를 원하지 않습니다. 다음 단어 이름이 무엇인지 이미 알려줍니다.
So, so yeah, that's kind of the reason we have zeros all after that, because we add a mask anyways.
그래서 그렇습니다. 어쨌든 마스크를 추가하기 때문에 그 이후에는 모두 0이 되는 이유가 됩니다.
So yeah, uh, this is the same idea and m is a head specific constant specified before training.
그래, 어, 이것도 같은 생각이고 m은 훈련 전에 지정된 머리 특정 상수입니다.
And this is the, with n heads, this will be set, set m to b.
그리고 이것은 n개의 머리로 설정될 것입니다. m을 b로 설정합니다.
And that's just, I guess the number that worked well for them. And these, they observed that
그리고 그것은 단지 그들에게 잘 맞는 숫자인 것 같아요. 그리고 그들은 이것을 관찰했습니다.
trainable m's didn't work well, and slopes between zero and one
훈련 가능한 m은 제대로 작동하지 않았고 0과 1 사이의 기울기가 있었습니다.
that had a higher density around zero worked well.
0 부근의 밀도가 더 높은 것이 잘 작동했습니다.
Uh, so yeah, so, so this is, each head is going to have a different m.
어, 그럼 그렇지, 그럼, 이건, 각 머리의 m이 다를 것입니다.
And therefore, it's going to take
따라서 시간이 걸릴 것입니다.
l times l times n space, where l is basically,
l 곱하기 l 곱하기 n 공간, 여기서 l은 기본적으로,
we kind of, kind of like mixed up the terminology here, l is the length of the,
우리는 여기서 용어를 혼동한 것 같습니다. l은 길이입니다.
the context and it's l times l, because that's the size of q, k, t.
문맥에 따르면 그것은 l 곱하기 l입니다. 왜냐하면 그것은 q, k, t의 크기이기 때문입니다.
And you have, you kind of have to have a different, um, a different n for every head.
그리고 여러분은 모든 머리에 대해 서로 다른, 음, 서로 다른 n을 가져야 합니다.
So, so I did a different m for every head. So, so you keep a q, k, t for every head.
그래서 저는 머리마다 다른 m을 사용했습니다. 따라서 모든 머리에 대해 aq, k, t를 유지합니다.
So that's why it takes that much space. So it's also applied to every layer, just like sinusoidal.
그래서 공간이 많이 필요한 거죠. 따라서 정현파처럼 모든 레이어에도 적용됩니다.
Um, we can also talk about perplexity here. So this is just basically explaining what
음, 여기서 당혹감에 대해서도 이야기할 수 있습니다. 그래서 이것은 기본적으로 무엇을 설명하는 것입니다.
perplexity is. So we want the LM to be able to assign real, real sentences, high probabilities.
당혹감은. 그래서 우리는 LM이 실제, 실제 문장, 높은 확률을 할당할 수 있기를 원합니다.
That's the idea. Um, and perplexity is some function of this probability function.
그것이 바로 아이디어입니다. 음, 그리고 당혹감은 이 확률 함수의 일부 함수입니다.
So basically, lower perplexity is better. And just to comparison between alibi versus sinusoidal,
따라서 기본적으로 당혹도가 낮을수록 좋습니다. 그리고 알리바이와 정현파를 비교하자면,
um, with, with alibi trained on half the tokens compared to the sinusoidal one, um,
음, 정현파 토큰에 비해 절반의 토큰에 대해 알리바이가 훈련되었습니다. 음,
alibi performs around the same as the sinusoidal one when tested on the longer sequence that
알리바이는 더 긴 시퀀스에서 테스트할 때 정현파와 거의 동일하게 수행됩니다.
sinusoidal was trained on, even though it uses, it's faster and uses less memory.
정현파는 훈련을 받았지만 사용하더라도 더 빠르고 더 적은 메모리를 사용합니다.
And here are some results. Um, they're all Trino 512 tokens here. As you can see, alibi stays,
그리고 여기에 몇 가지 결과가 있습니다. 음, 여기는 모두 Trino 512 토큰이에요. 보시다시피 알리바이는 유지됩니다.
stays pretty good. While the others just diverge. The same here for 10,000, 10,024 tokens.
꽤 잘 지내요. 다른 것들은 단지 갈라지는 반면. 10,000, 10,024개의 토큰에 대해서도 마찬가지입니다.
And here you can see that alibi extrapolates pretty well. Trino 512 where sinusoidal, um,
그리고 여기에서 알리바이가 꽤 잘 추정된다는 것을 볼 수 있습니다. Trino 512 여기서 정현파, 음,
when trained on 512, it doesn't, basically performs here. And you don't really see the next one
512에서 훈련하면 기본적으로 여기서는 수행되지 않습니다. 그리고 넌 다음 장면을 전혀 볼 수 없어
because it explodes. And, uh, that's the same phenomenon here. Just explodes. So the performance
폭발하기 때문이죠. 그리고, 어, 여기서도 같은 현상이군요. 그냥 폭발합니다. 그래서 성능은
just, um, it's very poor as, as soon as you increase the input length by a little bit,
음, 입력 길이를 조금 늘리자마자
but alibi does, does fine. And, um, here's the validation perplexity. And it shows that alibi,
하지만 알리바이는 괜찮아요. 그리고 음, 여기에 검증의 복잡성이 있습니다. 그리고 그것은 알리바이를 보여줍니다.
um, trained on half the tokens, does just as well on, on the tokens, basically that
음, 토큰의 절반에 대해 훈련을 받았지만 토큰에 대해서는 기본적으로 다음과 같은 일을 잘 수행합니다.
playing, playing sinusoidal's game here, basically on 10,024 tokens. And here is basically 2048 tokens.
기본적으로 10,024개의 토큰으로 정현파 게임을 플레이하고 있습니다. 그리고 여기에는 기본적으로 2048개의 토큰이 있습니다.
Okay. So now I'll be going over multi-query attention. Multi-query attention is basically
좋아요. 이제 다중 쿼리 주의를 살펴보겠습니다. 다중 쿼리 주의는 기본적으로
reusing the same, um, the same WQK, okay, V, okay, KQKV matrices across different heads.
동일한, 음, 동일한 WQK, 알았어, V, 알았어, KQKV 행렬을 다른 헤드에 걸쳐 재사용합니다.
So usually we would have one of these for every single head. So it looks something like this.
그래서 일반적으로 우리는 각 머리마다 이것들 중 하나를 갖게 됩니다. 그래서 그것은 다음과 같습니다.
But now, uh, we all, we use this, if we use the same one, then it looks something like this. And
하지만 지금은, 어, 우리 모두 이것을 사용합니다. 동일한 것을 사용하면 다음과 같이 보입니다. 그리고
that's supposed to give us speed up because we only have one matrix. Um, attention basics,
우리는 행렬이 하나뿐이기 때문에 속도가 빨라질 것으로 예상됩니다. 음, 주의 기본 사항은
I won't be going over it again. And yeah, let me just, uh, I won't go through the in-depth analysis
나는 그것에 대해 다시 다루지 않을 것입니다. 그리고 네, 그냥, 어, 심층적인 분석은 하지 않겠습니다
here, but let me tell you what, what, at least with, with each of these variables mean. So
여기서는 각 변수가 무엇을 의미하는지, 적어도 with가 무엇을 의미하는지 말씀드리겠습니다. 그래서
basically X is your, um, is your input matrix and it has context length N.
기본적으로 X는 음, 입력 행렬이고 컨텍스트 길이는 N입니다.
And this is the input to your encoder.
그리고 이것은 인코더에 대한 입력입니다.
And this is the M is the input to your decoder, basically. And then this has length M.
그리고 이것은 M이 기본적으로 디코더의 입력입니다. 그리고 이것은 길이 M을 가집니다.
So D is the, is the size of every word embedding.
따라서 D는 모든 단어 임베딩의 크기입니다.
Um, H is the number of heads. B is the batch that you're taking this over.
음, H는 앞면의 수입니다. B는 당신이 이것을 인계받는 배치입니다.
Um, and yeah, K, K and V are the sizes of W, K and WV.
음, 네, K, K, V는 W, K, WV의 크기입니다.
And yeah, I think that should be all. And basically what we want is we want the total
그리고 네, 그게 전부라고 생각합니다. 기본적으로 우리가 원하는 것은 총계를 원하는 것입니다.
memory access of multi head attention to be, and not to confuse multi head attention with
멀티 헤드 어텐션의 메모리 액세스는 멀티 헤드 어텐션과 혼동하지 않아야 합니다.
multi query intention, which is the, which is what we're covering here. Multi head attention is
다중 쿼리 의도가 바로 여기서 다루는 내용입니다. 멀티헤드 어텐션은
the original attention mechanism suggested and attention is all you need. So, um, here we have,
제안된 원래 주의 메커니즘과 주의만 있으면 됩니다. 음, 여기 있습니다.
we have memories to operation ratio for training. You know, it's, it's a lot less than one. It's
훈련을 위한 메모리 대 작업 비율이 있습니다. 알다시피, 그것은 1보다 훨씬 적습니다. 그것은
one over K, um, K is about here. And plus one over BN, which should be a lot less than one.
1 나누기 K, 음, K는 여기쯤이에요. 그리고 BN에 1을 더하면 1보다 훨씬 작아야 합니다.
But for inference, it becomes N over D plus one over B. And one over B, it's easy to deal with.
하지만 추론을 위해서는 D 분의 N 더하기 B 분의 1이 됩니다. 그리고 B 분의 1은 다루기가 쉽습니다.
We just increase the batch size to be larger. But N over D is something that we might need to worry
배치 크기를 더 크게 늘립니다. 하지만 N/D는 우리가 걱정해야 할 부분입니다
about. Um, when, when our context length is roughly, uh, for example, if our complex length
에 대한. 음, 컨텍스트 길이가 대략적으로 같을 때, 예를 들어 복잡한 길이가
is like a thousand words or something, and, and our date, the value of D, um, which is the dimension
천 단어 정도이고, 그리고 우리 날짜는 D의 값, 음, 차원입니다.
of, of each, each embedding, uh, word embedding, it's also like around the thousand, then we might
각각의 각 임베딩, 어, 단어 임베딩도 약 1,000개에 달합니다. 그러면 우리는
need to worry because it's not, this is not a lot less than one anymore.
그렇지 않기 때문에 걱정할 필요가 있습니다. 이것은 더 이상 1보다 적지 않습니다.
And so yeah, it's, it's very, it's a very simple idea. We just basically use one. We can see here,
네, 그렇습니다. 매우 간단한 아이디어입니다. 우리는 기본적으로 하나만 사용합니다. 여기서 볼 수 있는 것은,
we had the PK, we had H of them for each head and the D times K. Um, but as soon as we use
우리는 PK를 가지고 있었고, 각 머리에 H개와 D 곱하기 K가 있었습니다. 음, 하지만 우리가 사용하자마자
multi-query attention, it's now just DK and DV. Uh, and I guess here we don't actually need to,
다중 쿼리 주의, 이제 DK와 DV만 남았습니다. 어, 그리고 여기서는 실제로 그럴 필요는 없을 것 같습니다.
we don't actually need to worry about, we don't actually need to worry about PQ here because,
우리는 실제로 걱정할 필요가 없습니다. 여기서는 실제로 PQ에 대해 걱정할 필요가 없습니다. 왜냐하면,
um, because we're dealing with an encoder, decoder task. So the bottleneck comes from
음, 우리는 인코더, 디코더 작업을 다루고 있기 때문입니다. 병목 현상은 다음과 같습니다.
repeatedly reloading K and V. So if you think about it, if I want to like do inference again
K와 V를 반복적으로 다시 로드합니다. 그러니 생각해 보면 내가 좋아하고 싶다면 다시 추론을 하세요.
with like my name is Matthew, and if we wanted to like translate it into like French or something,
내 이름은 매튜인데, 프랑스어 같은 것으로 번역하고 싶다면
it would be like, je m'appelle. Okay, my French is not good enough for this, uh, Mathieu or something.
그것은 마치, je m'appelle과 같을 것입니다. 알았어, 내 프랑스어 실력은 이 일을 하기엔 부족해, 어, 마티유든 뭐든.
So, um, so suppose that we're doing, we're doing, we're doing this task and we start with
음, 우리가 지금 하고 있다고 가정해 보세요, 우리가 하고 있어요, 우리가 이 일을 하고 있고, 우리가 시작하는 것은
my, the word my, um, at inference, what we need to do is, uh, at inference, we have this entire
나의, 나의, 음, 추론에서 우리가 해야 할 일은, 어, 추론에서 우리는 이 전체를 가지고 있습니다.
query. My name is Matthew, um, and we want to translate it. And the first time we're gonna,
질문. 제 이름은 매튜입니다. 음, 우리는 그것을 번역하고 싶습니다. 그리고 처음으로 우리는
we're gonna get, and then, um, the Q, the PQ, or like the Q matrix is going to remain the same.
우리는 얻을 것이고, 음, Q, PQ, 또는 Q 행렬과 같은 것은 동일하게 유지될 것입니다.
Q equal to PQ and X, but, um, the K and V are going to equal to P, K, V, multiplied by M.
Q는 PQ 및 X와 같지만, 음, K와 V는 P, K, V에 M을 곱한 것과 같습니다.
This M is going to keep on changing. The input to our decoder is going to keep on changing because
이 M은 계속 변할 것입니다. 디코더에 대한 입력은 계속해서 변경될 것입니다.
after the first word, we have a, and then we have, uh, my, and then we have my,
첫 번째 단어 뒤에는 a가 있고 그 다음에는 uh, my가 있고 그 다음에는 my,
so we're gonna have to keep on reloading this K and V, and that's where the bottleneck comes from.
그래서 우리는 이 K와 V를 계속해서 다시 로드해야 하며, 여기서 병목 현상이 발생합니다.
Um, so yeah, during training, you know, it still does pretty well. No surprises here,
음, 그래, 훈련 중에도 여전히 꽤 잘 지내고 있어. 여기서는 놀랄 일이 아닙니다.
but for during inferences is where this multi-query attention release shines.
하지만 추론하는 동안에는 이 다중 쿼리 주의 릴리스가 빛을 발합니다.
So before when, where we had, uh, N over D, um, which is, which is what we wanted to reduce.
그래서 이전에는, 어, D 나누기 N이 있었는데, 음, 이것이 우리가 줄이고 싶었던 것입니다.
Now we have N over DH. Uh, we basically, because we, we had, we reduced the number of,
이제 DH에 대한 N이 있습니다. 어, 기본적으로 우리는 숫자를 줄였기 때문에,
number of Ks and Vs that we wanted to reload by a factor of H, it shows through here. Um,
H배로 다시 로드하려는 K 및 V의 수는 여기를 통해 표시됩니다. 음,
so, so, so then the memory to operation ratio is getting to Ketflow, and that's why multi-query
그래서, 그래서, 메모리 대 작업 비율이 Ketflow에 도달하고 있으며, 이것이 바로 다중 쿼리가 수행되는 이유입니다.
attention works pretty well. Uh, okay, so, so let's look at some results. Um,
주의는 꽤 잘 작동합니다. 아, 그렇군요. 그럼 몇 가지 결과를 살펴보겠습니다. 음,
so here, here are basically how, uh, how they perform.
여기 기본적으로 어떻게, 어, 어떻게 작동하는지 나와 있습니다.
Um, you can see that multi-head still performs the best, uh, because it does have, have more heads,
음, 다중 헤드가 여전히 최고의 성능을 발휘한다는 것을 알 수 있습니다. 왜냐하면 더 많은 헤드가 있기 때문입니다.
but multi-query is comparable to it. And, uh, and same, the same for here. Multi-head
하지만 다중 쿼리는 이와 비슷합니다. 그리고, 어, 그리고 똑같습니다. 여기서도 마찬가지입니다. 멀티헤드
that's the best, uh, but multi-query, it's, you know, it's, it's comfortable. Um, and,
그게 최고야, 어, 하지만 다중 쿼리는, 그게, 그게, 그게, 편해. 음, 그리고,
and to look at the time that we saved, uh, here, again, if you look at the encoder time,
그리고 우리가 저장한 시간을 보면, 어, 여기, 다시 인코더 시간을 보면,
it's all around the same because Q remains the same. This is the, this is the translation task.
Q가 동일하게 유지되기 때문에 모든 것이 동일합니다. 이것이 바로 번역 작업입니다.
So Q remains the same. It's always going to be, my name is Matthew, but, um, so, so, so, you know,
따라서 Q는 동일하게 유지됩니다. 제 이름은 매튜인데, 음, 그러니까, 그러니까, 그러니까, 아시다시피,
multi-query attention really didn't speed anything up there, but for the decoder part,
다중 쿼리 주의는 실제로 속도를 높이지는 못했지만 디코더 부분에서는
we have to constantly reload my, my, my, so by doing that, um, we waste a lot of time if we reload
my, my, my를 계속해서 다시 로드해야 하므로 그렇게 하면 음, 다시 로드하면 많은 시간을 낭비하게 됩니다.
H as, H times as many more heads and multi-head versus multi-query. So, yeah, so, so that's,
H만큼, H배 더 많은 헤드와 멀티 헤드 대 멀티 쿼리. 그러니까, 그래, 그러니까, 그러니까,
that's a lot faster here. Um, yeah. So, so, so there's still some problems with multi-query
여기가 훨씬 빠릅니다. 음, 응. 그래서 다중 쿼리에는 여전히 몇 가지 문제가 있습니다.
attention. Uh, they're basically just two, two, two big problems. The first problem is that
주목. 어, 기본적으로 두 가지, 두 가지, 두 가지 큰 문제일 뿐입니다. 첫 번째 문제는
if we already have, you know, we were like the open AI trained GPT for spend like $2 billion
이미 가지고 있다면 우리는 20억 달러 정도의 지출을 위해 개방형 AI 교육을 받은 GPT와 같았습니다.
on it or something. And then now you say, Oh, you know, what you really should do to speed up your
그것에 대해 또는 뭔가. 그리고 이제 당신은 '아, 당신이 정말 속도를 높이기 위해 무엇을 해야 하는지 알잖아'라고 말합니다.
inference is use multi-query attention and, but you, when you started training the model, you
추론은 다중 쿼리 주의를 사용하는 것이지만, 모델 학습을 시작하면
used multi-head attention. So, you know, what are you going to do now? Are you going to train,
다중 헤드 주의를 사용했습니다. 그럼 이제 무엇을 할 건가요? 훈련할 것인가,
train the model from scratch and spend like another like a billion dollars on the training?
모델을 처음부터 훈련시키고 훈련에 수십억 달러를 지출하시겠습니까?
Or is there a faster way to adapt your existing model, um, to multi-query attention? So it's
아니면 기존 모델을 다중 쿼리 주의에 적용하는 더 빠른 방법이 있습니까? 그래서 그것은
faster during inference. Um, so the answer is affirmative. There is, it's called up training.
추론하는 동안 더 빠릅니다. 음, 대답은 긍정이에요. 훈련이라고 불리는 것이 있습니다.
And another thing is that we want to find an intermediate stage between having, you know,
또 다른 점은 우리가 갖는 것 사이의 중간 단계를 찾고자 한다는 것입니다.
like in this example, having, having, uh, eight, eight, like here, there's eight heads. I'll
이 예에서처럼, 어, 8, 8개, 여기처럼 8개의 머리가 있습니다. 아픈
sharing this one, I'll sharing one, uh, k, kv matrix and having eight separate, uh, kv matrices.
이것을 공유하면 하나의 어, k, kv 행렬을 공유하고 8개의 별도의 어, kv 행렬을 갖게 됩니다.
We want to find some, some, somewhere in between. So what it would have felt like two of them,
우리는 그 사이 어딘가에서 일부를 찾고 싶습니다. 그렇다면 두 사람이 어떤 느낌이었을지,
for example. Um, so that's called group query attention. That's how that's we're going to cover
예를 들어. 음, 그건 그룹 쿼리 어텐션(group query attention)이라고 하는 거죠. 그게 바로 우리가 다룰 내용이야
next. Um, so we're first going to cover up, up training and idea is very simple. Uh, so we basically,
다음. 음, 먼저 은폐하려고 합니다. 훈련과 아이디어는 매우 간단합니다. 어, 그래서 우리는 기본적으로
we basically have our original, um, for example, we already had our original, you know, k, k, uh,
기본적으로 원본이 있습니다. 음, 예를 들어 이미 원본이 있습니다. k, k, 어,
k different projection matrices and we take the mean and we say, okay, now we have a new,
k개의 서로 다른 투영 행렬을 사용하고 평균을 취하여 다음과 같이 말합니다. 이제 새로운 것이 생겼습니다.
new projection matrix. Uh, um, and this might not work well at first, but we're, we're going to say,
새로운 투영 매트릭스. 어, 음, 처음에는 잘 안 될 수도 있겠지만, 우리는, 이렇게 말하겠습니다.
okay, we're going to train it with multi-query attention and they're, and then it turns out,
좋습니다. 우리는 다중 쿼리 주의를 기울여 훈련할 예정입니다. 그리고 결과는 다음과 같습니다.
if we just do 5% of the original training steps, this, this matrix turns out to be good enough.
원래 훈련 단계의 5%만 수행하면 이 행렬은 충분히 좋은 것으로 나타납니다.
We can also randomly initialize it. Uh, it doesn't do a, it's not, it doesn't, it doesn't work as well.
무작위로 초기화할 수도 있습니다. 어, 안 돼요, 안 돼, 안 돼, 잘 안 돼요.
And we can also initialize it from like, uh, a particular key projection matrix also doesn't
그리고 우리는 또한 그것을 초기화할 수도 있습니다. 어, 특정 키 투영 행렬도 그렇지 않습니다.
work as well. Uh, the meaningful works the best. Um, and for the other thing I was talking about,
일도. 어, 의미 있는 것이 가장 잘 작동합니다. 음, 그리고 제가 얘기하고 있던 또 다른 점은
instead of having, you know, only one, we can maybe have like four and separate these two,
하나만 갖는 대신에 4개 정도를 갖고 이 두 개를 분리할 수도 있습니다.
these heads into four groups. So two of them share a single one. So, you know, this is sort of in
이들은 네 그룹으로 나뉜다. 그래서 두 사람이 하나를 공유합니다. 알다시피, 이것은 일종의
between and, um, uh, up training can also be applied to group query. Uh, namely we just,
사이, 음, 어, 업 트레이닝은 그룹 쿼리에도 적용될 수 있습니다. 어, 즉 우리는 단지,
we just pulled these two heads, me and pulled these two heads into this one and train.
우리는 이 두 개의 머리를 잡아당겼고, 저는 이 두 개의 머리를 이것으로 끌어당겨 훈련시켰습니다.
Okay. So the benefits of group query attention. So one is that it might be like a natural trade
좋아요. 따라서 그룹 쿼리 관심의 이점은 다음과 같습니다. 그래서 하나는 그것이 자연 거래와 같을 수도 있다는 것입니다.
off between MQA and MHA between performance and time. Um, you know, it's going to have,
성능과 시간 사이에는 MQA와 MHA 사이의 차이가 있습니다. 음, 알다시피, 그럴 것입니다.
in terms of speed, it's going to be somewhere in the middle, but in terms of,
속도 측면에서는 중간 정도가 되겠지만, 측면에서는
in terms of performance, it's always, it's also going to be somewhere in the middle.
성능 측면에서는 항상 중간 정도일 것입니다.
And it might be just be the best middle ground. Um, and moreover, if you consider MQA,
그리고 그것은 단지 최고의 중간 지점일 수도 있습니다. 음, 게다가 MQA를 고려한다면,
where, you know, eight of these, eight of these heads,
아시다시피 이 중 8개, 이 머리 중 8개는
I'll share a single, uh, I'll share a single projection matrix. Um,
저는 하나의 프로젝션 매트릭스를 공유하겠습니다. 음,
in standard charting, this matrix might be, you know, these four might be grouped into one
표준 차트에서 이 행렬은 이 네 개가 하나로 그룹화될 수 있습니다.
chart and these four might need to grouped into another chart. And this, this, uh, this,
차트가 있으며 이 4개는 다른 차트로 그룹화해야 할 수도 있습니다. 그리고 이거, 이거, 어, 이거,
this projection matrix here will have to, would originally have to been copied twice anyways.
여기 이 투영 행렬은 원래 어쨌든 두 번 복사되어야 합니다.
So, you know, that's kind of saying, you know, if, if, if it was going to cost this much memory
그러니까, 아시다시피, 이 정도의 메모리 비용이 든다면,
anyways, why not just do GQA? And now in terms of GQA results, as you can see, um, in terms of time,
어쨌든, 그냥 GQA를 하면 안 되나요? 이제 GQA 결과를 보면, 보시다시피 시간 측면에서 보면
it's comparable to MQA, but it beats MQA performance. And in terms of performance,
MQA와 비슷하지만 MQA 성능을 능가합니다. 그리고 성능면에서는
it's comparable to MHA, but it beats it in time. Um, and here's a, here's a graph showing the trade
MHA와 비슷하지만 시간이 지나면 이깁니다. 음, 여기 거래를 보여주는 그래프가 있습니다.
off between GQA, uh, as the number of groups increase. So at one, basically, um, GQA is basically
그룹 수가 늘어나면 GQA 사이에서 떨어져요. 기본적으로, 음, GQA는 기본적으로
equivalent to MQA. Um, but as you scale it up, it's going to take, uh, I mean, it's going to take
MQA와 동일합니다. 음, 하지만 규모를 확대하면 시간이 걸릴 것입니다. 어, 내 말은, 시간이 걸릴 것이라는 뜻입니다.
more time to sample. Uh, and that's basically shows the trade off. And here, uh, it shows the trade
샘플링하는 데 더 많은 시간이 걸립니다. 어, 그리고 그것은 기본적으로 절충안을 보여줍니다. 그리고 여기, 어, 거래가 표시됩니다
off between again, time and the performance. So as you can see, MHA here has the highest time,
다시, 시간과 공연 사이에. 보시다시피 여기 MHA가 가장 높은 시간을 가지고 있습니다.
but also has the performance. And MQA has the, um, lowest time, but you know, also a decent
성능도 있습니다. 그리고 MQA는 음, 가장 낮은 시간을 가지고 있지만 알다시피 괜찮은 수준이기도 합니다.
performance. I mean, let's ignore this one. And out of the three has the lowest performance. And
성능. 내 말은, 이건 무시하자는 거죠. 그리고 3개 중 성능이 가장 낮습니다. 그리고
for GQA with, with eight groups, it has, you know, relatively good time and relatively good performance.
8개 그룹으로 구성된 GQA의 경우 상대적으로 좋은 시간과 상대적으로 좋은 성과를 거두었습니다.
And here are the results for up training. As you can see, when we take the mean, um,
그리고 업 트레이닝 결과는 다음과 같습니다. 보시다시피, 평균을 취하면 음,
that's, that achieved the best performance with alpha equal to 0.05. And, uh,
즉, 알파가 0.05일 때 최고의 성능을 달성한 것입니다. 그리고, 어,
you can see here with alpha equal to 0.05, we can kind of achieve comparable performance
여기에서 알파가 0.05인 것을 볼 수 있습니다. 비슷한 성능을 얻을 수 있습니다.
with GQA and slightly worth within QA. Then with 1%, uh, basically identical performance
GQA와 함께하고 QA 내에서는 약간의 가치가 있습니다. 그럼 1%면, 어, 기본적으로 동일한 성능
with GQA and worth with MQA. Okay. And now, uh, I'm done my section on, on my, on group query
GQA와 함께라면 MQA와 함께라면 가치가 있습니다. 좋아요. 그리고 이제, 어, 그룹 쿼리에 대한 섹션을 마쳤습니다.
and multi query retention. And I'll move to IO aware based methods, uh, namely flash attention.
다중 쿼리 보존. 그리고 저는 IO 인식 기반 방법, 즉 플래시 어텐션(Flash Attention)으로 이동할 것입니다.
Um, so basically previous attention speed ups, um, many of them, you know, for example,
음, 기본적으로 이전의 주의 속도 향상은 음, 그 중 많은 부분이 예를 들어
they have sparser attention or low rank approximation. Um, the, the, they, what they
관심이 적거나 순위 근사치가 낮습니다. 음, 그, 그, 그, 그, 그들이 무엇을
don't focus on is input out being input and output aware. And what I mean by that is being,
입력 및 출력을 인식하는 입력 출력에 중점을 두지 마십시오. 제가 의미하는 바는 존재한다는 것입니다.
being using the SRAM, the in chip SRAM in a smart way. They don't, they don't take that into
SRAM, 즉 인칩 SRAM을 스마트하게 사용하고 있습니다. 그들은 그렇지 않습니다. 그들은 그것을 받아들이지 않습니다.
consideration. Um, and flash attention thinks about this and uses SRAM in a very smart way.
고려 사항. 음, 그리고 플래시 어텐션은 이것에 대해 생각하고 SRAM을 매우 똑똑한 방식으로 사용합니다.
So that, uh, there are fewer access to, to HBM, um, which is basically a larger, but slower memory.
그래서, 음, 기본적으로 더 크지만 느린 메모리인 HBM에 대한 액세스가 더 적습니다.
Yeah. So to give you some basics about this HBM and SRAM, there's like 40 to 80 gigabytes of HBM.
응. 따라서 이 HBM과 SRAM에 대한 몇 가지 기본 사항을 알려드리자면 HBM의 용량은 40~80GB 정도 됩니다.
You know, it's, it's not that fast and there's a much smaller SRAM unit, but it is much faster.
아시다시피, 그다지 빠르지는 않고 SRAM 장치도 훨씬 작지만 훨씬 빠릅니다.
So the idea is that instead of, um, instead of doing many trips of HBM, reason rights, like,
그래서 아이디어는, 음, HBM을 많이 여행하는 대신, 이유 권리는 다음과 같습니다.
suppose that this is the HBM, um, and this is your SRAM, this is your, um, this is your CPU,
이것이 HBM이고, 음, 이것이 SRAM이고, 이것이 여러분의, 음, 이것이 여러분의 CPU라고 가정해 보세요.
or sorry, GPU. This is where you like, this is where you, this is, this is your unit, this is
아니면 미안해요, GPU. 여기가 네가 좋아하는 곳이야, 여기가 네가 있는 곳이야, 여기가 네 유닛이야, 이게 바로
the processing unit. Basically, you can think of it as retrieving information. If you keep on,
처리 장치. 기본적으로는 정보를 검색하는 것이라고 생각하시면 됩니다. 계속하다 보면,
you know, sending stuff from HBM and then sending it back, going forward, sending it back,
아시다시피, HBM에서 물건을 보내고 다시 보내고, 계속해서 다시 보내고,
it's going to take a long time. But if instead what you do is you, you say, okay, first I'm going to
시간이 오래 걸릴 거예요. 하지만 만약 당신이 하는 일이 당신이라면, 당신은 '알겠습니다. 먼저 내가 할게요'라고 말합니다.
read from HBM and then I'm going to take, put some intermediate back, not all the way back to HBM,
HBM에서 읽은 다음 HBM으로 다시 가져오는 것이 아니라 중간체를 다시 넣을 것입니다.
because that's going to take way too long, but I'm going to put some intermediate back into SRAM
시간이 너무 오래 걸리기 때문에 SRAM에 중간체를 다시 넣을 예정입니다.
and then process again and then do some of this and then go all the way back to HBM.
그런 다음 다시 처리하고 이 중 일부를 수행한 다음 HBM으로 돌아갑니다.
You know, this, that's going to be a loss, a lot more cost effective and that's the idea behind
알다시피, 이것은 손실이 될 것이고, 훨씬 더 비용 효율적일 것입니다. 그리고 이것이 바로 뒤에 있는 아이디어입니다.
flash attention. And, um, you know, just, just for some reminder of the matrix dimensions and,
플래시주의. 그리고, 음, 아시다시피, 행렬 차원을 다시 한번 상기시켜 드리고,
you know, storing takes a one squared memory because, because of this. And, and, uh, yeah,
아시다시피, 저장하려면 1제곱 메모리가 필요합니다. 왜냐하면 이것 때문입니다. 그리고, 그리고, 어, 그래,
so, so, so let's get into flash attention. And before that, let's just go over standard
그래서, 그래서, 플래시 어텐션에 대해 알아봅시다. 그리고 그 전에 표준을 넘어가자
attention again. And this is the thing I was talking about, um, about going back and forth between
다시 주목. 그리고 이것이 바로 제가 이야기하고 있던 것입니다. 음, 두 가지 사이를 오가는 것에 대한 것입니다.
HBM and the processing unit. So, you know, here you load from HBM, you write it back, you load,
HBM 및 처리 장치. 아시다시피, 여기 HBM에서 로드하고, 다시 쓰고, 로드하고,
you know, you load, you load it, you write it back, you load it again, you write it back again,
알다시피, 로드하고, 로드하고, 다시 쓰고, 다시 로드하고, 다시 쓰고,
you load it again, you write it back again, and finally you return it.
다시 로드하고, 다시 쓰고, 마지막으로 반환합니다.
Um, you know, that's, that's, that's not the smartest way to do things and it doesn't really
음, 아시다시피, 그건, 그게, 그건 일을 하는 가장 현명한 방법도 아니고 실제로도 그렇지 않습니다
use SRAM to speed this process up. Um, so the idea, the idea is that we can use SRAM. Well,
이 프로세스의 속도를 높이려면 SRAM을 사용하십시오. 음, 그래서 아이디어는 우리가 SRAM을 사용할 수 있다는 것입니다. 잘,
how can we use it? So first of all, we can use this method called tiling, which basically says,
우리는 그것을 어떻게 사용할 수 있나요? 먼저 타일링이라는 방법을 사용할 수 있습니다. 기본적으로는 다음과 같습니다.
okay, so this is your SRAM here. You break it up into, um, a few different slots.
좋아요, 여기가 SRAM이군요. 당신은 그것을 몇 개의 다른 슬롯으로 나눕니다.
We dedicate one slot for the Q, one slot for K, one slot for V, and one slot for O.
Q에 한 슬롯, K에 한 슬롯, V에 한 슬롯, O에 한 슬롯을 할당합니다.
And then here we dedicate two, you know, smaller linear slots for L, and then another for M,
그런 다음 여기서는 두 개의 더 작은 선형 슬롯을 L에 할당하고 다른 하나는 M에 할당합니다.
and I'll explain what they mean after. Um, so the final goal of what we want to achieve,
나중에 그 의미를 설명하겠습니다. 음, 그럼 우리가 이루고 싶은 최종 목표는,
so suppose that we originally, we started with your Xs. What we want to do is we want to compute
그래서 우리가 원래 X로 시작했다고 가정해 보겠습니다. 우리가 하고 싶은 것은 계산을 하는 것입니다.
your, um, your, your Q, K, T, and then we want to take the softmax of it.
당신의, 음, 당신의 Q, K, T 그리고 우리는 그것의 소프트맥스를 취하고 싶습니다.
And the reason, okay, so, so, okay, so what does the softmax function look like? Okay,
그 이유는, 그렇죠, 그렇죠, 그렇죠, 소프트맥스 함수는 어떤 모습일까요? 좋아요,
so suppose that this matrix, okay,
그럼 이 행렬이 다음과 같다고 가정해 보세요.
suppose that this matrix is only a single vector, um, we want to do is take the exp,
이 행렬이 단일 벡터라고 가정하면, 음, 우리가 하고 싶은 것은 exp를 취하는 것입니다.
we take it to, to, to, to, to the exponential and then we subtract by the maximum.
우리는 그것을 지수 함수로 취한 다음 최대값을 뺍니다.
And then we divide it by this L, which is the sum across all of them.
그런 다음 이를 L로 나눕니다. L은 모든 항목의 합입니다.
Um, this is L. And, uh, that's basically our end goal.
음, 이쪽은 L입니다. 그리고 음, 그게 기본적으로 우리의 최종 목표입니다.
Now, because the SRM is so small, each time it's impossible for us to load an entire Q
이제 SRM이 너무 작기 때문에 매번 전체 Q를 로드하는 것이 불가능합니다.
or entire K or entire V. So we can only, we can only compute a very smart part of it,
또는 전체 K 또는 전체 V. 따라서 우리는 그것의 아주 똑똑한 부분만 계산할 수 있습니다.
a small part of it, uh, at once, and we'll have to concatenate them together. The problem is that
그것의 작은 부분을, 어, 한 번에, 그리고 우리는 그것들을 하나로 연결해야 할 것입니다. 문제는
there's a softmax outside of Q, K, T. So, um, if our final goal is, this is, okay, this is without
Q, K, T 외부에 소프트맥스가 있습니다. 음, 최종 목표가 다음이라면 이것은, 좋습니다.
the softmax Q, K, T, V, uh, just for illustration, FR, and basically this is, uh, this is our O
소프트맥스 Q, K, T, V, 어, 설명을 위한 FR이고, 기본적으로 이것은, 어, 이것이 우리의 O입니다.
without the softmax. If our final goal is to compute something like this
소프트맥스 없이. 우리의 최종 목표가 다음과 같은 것을 계산하는 것이라면
and each time we only have like Q, Q, like a small component of Q. So, so suppose that this is an
그리고 매번 우리는 Q의 작은 구성요소인 Q, Q만을 갖게 됩니다. 그래서 이것이
entire Q, uh, this is Q. And this, each time we only load a little bit of Q and we load, uh, this
전체 Q, 어, 이게 Q입니다. 그리고 이것은, 우리가 Q를 아주 조금만 로드할 때마다, 어, 이것을 로드합니다
is K, we only load a lit, this is KT, we only load a little bit of K. Um, so that means out of this
는 K이고, 우리는 약간만 로드하고, 이것은 KT이고, 우리는 K를 조금만 로드합니다. 음, 그러니까 이것은 밖으로 나가라는 뜻입니다
entire output, we only have like Q from one to like, maybe like somewhere here. And then K,
전체 출력에서 ​​우리는 하나에서 좋아요까지의 Q만 가지고 있습니다. 아마도 여기 어딘가와 같을 것입니다. 그리고 K,
uh, sorry, Q goes this way, Q goes this way. So Q, one to like somewhere here. And then K
어, 미안해요. Q는 이쪽으로 가요, Q는 이쪽으로 가요. Q, 여기 어딘가에 마음에 드는 것 하나. 그리고 K
from here to over here. So we only have like this part. And then what we have to compute is,
여기에서 여기까지. 그래서 우리는 이 부분만 가지고 있습니다. 그리고 우리가 계산해야 할 것은,
what we have, we do is we compute this and then we compute this, and we compute this,
우리가 하는 일은 이것을 계산하고 이것을 계산하고 또 이것을 계산하는 것입니다.
we compute this, and then we compute this and an added to this and then we compute this and added
이것을 계산하고, 이것을 계산하고 여기에 더하고, 이것을 계산하고 더합니다.
to this. Um, and then etc, so let me just draw that more clearly come first compute this little
이에. 음, 그리고 그다음에는 좀 더 명확하게 그려보겠습니다. 먼저 이 작은 것을 계산해 보세요.
part, and then this, and then this, and then compute this, and then add it to this, compute
부분, 그리고 이것, 그리고 이것, 그리고 이것을 계산하고, 이것에 더하고, 계산합니다.
this, add it to this, compute this, add it to this. Now the problem is that if we're
이것, 이것에 더하고, 이것을 계산하고, 이것에 더하세요. 이제 문제는 만약 우리가
taught, we have to take the softmax. So we can't just compute this and take its softmax
가르친 대로, 우리는 소프트맥스를 취해야 합니다. 따라서 우리는 이것을 계산하고 소프트맥스를 취할 수는 없습니다.
and then compute this and take its softmax and add it to this. You know, that doesn't
그런 다음 이것을 계산하고 소프트맥스를 가져와 여기에 추가합니다. 알잖아, 그건 그렇지 않아
work like that. You're going to get the wrong softmax values. So that's why we need to keep
그렇게 일하세요. 잘못된 소프트맥스 값을 얻게 됩니다. 그래서 우리가 지켜야 할 이유는
an array of m, which is the maximum of this row here, and then another array of l, which
여기 이 행의 최대값인 m의 배열, 그리고 또 다른 l의 배열,
is basically the sum here. And we're going to use this to finally compute the correct
기본적으로 여기에 있는 합계입니다. 그리고 우리는 이것을 사용하여 최종적으로 올바른 값을 계산할 것입니다.
softmax at the very end. Okay, so how do we do it? So high level idea. What we do is
맨 끝에는 소프트맥스가 있습니다. 좋아요, 그럼 어떻게 할까요? 너무 높은 수준의 아이디어입니다. 우리가 하는 일은
we start out with this. Yeah, maybe let me just go through the pseudo code or, yeah.
우리는 이것으로 시작합니다. 예, 어쩌면 의사 코드를 살펴보도록 하겠습니다. 아니면 예.
So the high level idea is that we do this, and then we do this and do this and do this.
그래서 높은 수준의 아이디어는 우리가 이것을 하고, 그런 다음 이것을 하고, 이것을 하고, 이것을 한다는 것입니다.
And then when we get to here, basically we normalize this by some factor. And when we
그리고 여기까지 오면 기본적으로 어떤 요인에 의해 이를 정규화합니다. 그리고 우리가
get to here, we multiply it by that factor again, and then divide this by the softmax
여기까지 와서 해당 요소를 다시 곱한 다음 이를 소프트맥스로 나눕니다.
for the entire thing. And then we repeat. So then when we get to the very end, we basically
모든 것에 대해. 그런 다음 반복합니다. 그래서 마지막에 도달하면 기본적으로
are multiplying, we have the entire thing divided by the alpha factor for everything.
곱하면 전체를 모든 것에 대한 알파 인수로 나눈 값이 있습니다.
So yeah, so let's take a look at the pseudo code. So we first loop on K and V. That means
네, 그럼 의사 코드를 살펴보겠습니다. 따라서 먼저 K와 V를 반복합니다. 즉
the inner loop is on Q and O. Yeah, maybe we should have this Q, O, K, V, L, M. This
내부 루프는 Q와 O에 있습니다. 예, 아마도 Q, O, K, V, L, M이 있어야 할 것입니다.
is our SRAM chip. We initially load K, K, I, KJ, VJ, which is basically like a subset
우리의 SRAM 칩입니다. 처음에는 기본적으로 하위 집합과 같은 K, K, I, KJ, VJ를 로드합니다.
of K and V. You can think of the entire matrix of K like this, KT. And then KJ is like some
K와 V의 전체 행렬을 KT라고 생각할 수 있습니다. 그리고 KJ는 좀 그렇죠
number of columns of K. And then V is some number of VJ. This is KJT. This is like VJT.
K의 열 수. 그리고 V는 VJ의 수입니다. KJT입니다. 이것은 VJT와 같습니다.
This is V. And the same for Q and O. So we load KJ, VJ from HBM onto SRAM. And if you
이것은 V입니다. Q와 O도 마찬가지입니다. 따라서 HBM에서 SRAM으로 KJ, VJ를 로드합니다. 만약 너라면
look at the final outputs of Q, KT, and V, that means we're trying to narrow down for,
Q, KT, V의 최종 출력을 살펴보세요. 이는 우리가 범위를 좁히려고 노력하고 있음을 의미합니다.
you know, for example, if J only includes two rows, then we're only looking at this group here.
예를 들어 J에 두 개의 행만 포함되어 있다면 여기서는 이 그룹만 살펴보겠습니다.
And then we loop over Q, which means we go down this way. And then we load Q and O.
그런 다음 Q를 반복합니다. 이는 우리가 이 방향으로 내려간다는 것을 의미합니다. 그런 다음 Q와 O를 로드합니다.
So we load the first one. And on chip, we compute Q, Q, I, J, Q, I, K, J, T. And so we first compute
그래서 우리는 첫 번째 것을 로드합니다. 그리고 칩에서는 Q, Q, I, J, Q, I, K, J, T를 계산합니다. 그래서 먼저 계산합니다.
this. And then we compute this. And then we compute this. And the question is, what do we do after
이것. 그리고 우리는 이것을 계산합니다. 그리고 우리는 이것을 계산합니다. 그리고 문제는, 그 후에 우리가 무엇을 하느냐는 것입니다.
every single one of them? Okay, so as an example, we first compute this here. And we compute the
하나하나? 좋아요, 예를 들어 먼저 여기서 이것을 계산해 보겠습니다. 그리고 우리는
max of this row. And then we normalize it with, we take this row, and then we take its value,
이 행의 최대값입니다. 그런 다음 이를 정규화하고 이 행을 취하고 그 값을 취합니다.
and we take it to the exponent. So we do exponent of all of these values to it. Oh,
그리고 우리는 그것을 지수로 가져갑니다. 그래서 우리는 이 모든 값을 그것에 지수화합니다. 오,
by the way, this is sorry, this is not the, this is not the intermediate value. This is the,
그건 그렇고, 죄송합니다. 이것은 중간 값이 아닙니다. 이것이,
what I should really be doing is towards this, this is Q, K, T. So we take a small component of it,
제가 정말로 해야 할 일은 이것에 대한 것입니다. 이것은 Q, K, T입니다. 그래서 우리는 그것의 작은 부분을 취합니다.
like somewhere here first. And then we look at each row. So for the first row, we look at the max,
먼저 여기 어딘가처럼요. 그런 다음 각 행을 살펴보겠습니다. 첫 번째 행에 대해 최대값을 살펴보겠습니다.
and then we do the exponent to this value minus the row max. And then the next value minus the row
그런 다음 이 값에서 행 최대값을 뺀 지수를 계산합니다. 그런 다음 행을 뺀 다음 값
max next value minus row max. And then we look at the next row and we say this row, this value
최대 다음 값에서 행 최대 값을 뺍니다. 그런 다음 다음 행을 보고 이 행, 이 값이라고 말합니다.
e to the this minus the max of this, etc. And then we divide by this L. And then we say,
e는 이것에서 이것의 최대값을 뺀 것입니다. 그런 다음 우리는 이 L로 나눕니다. 그리고 우리는 이렇게 말합니다.
okay, so let's let's look at if this, this maximum value. So suppose that we were like
좋습니다. 이것이 최대값인지 살펴보겠습니다. 그러니 우리가 다음과 같다고 가정해보자
somewhere in the middle here, if this maximum value were the max across all of these previous values. So
이 최대값이 이전 값 전체의 최대값이라면 여기 중간 어딘가에 있을 것입니다. 그래서
if we already did this part, already did this part, and then we're like looking at this partition.
이 부분을 이미 수행했다면 이 부분도 이미 수행한 것이며 이 파티션을 살펴보는 것과 같습니다.
So maybe like the third, the third K, K three or something. And then we're looking at Q one.
아마도 세 번째, 세 번째 K, K 3 등이 될 것입니다. 그리고 나서 우리는 Q 1을 보고 있습니다.
And we look at the maximum here, and we say, Oh, is this maximum, you know, is it larger than the previous two?
여기서 우리는 최대값을 보고 '아, 이 최대값이 이전 두 개보다 큰가요?'라고 말합니다.
So and then and then and then we take the maximum here, we take the true maximum here. And then for
그래서 계속해서 여기서 최대값을 취합니다. 여기에서 진정한 최대값을 취합니다. 그리고 나서
the previous two, we have the previously computed maximum here. And then we basically
이전 두 개에는 이전에 계산된 최대값이 있습니다. 그리고 우리는 기본적으로
multiply it by that maximum to get rid of it in the previous two terms that was already saved
이미 저장된 이전 두 항에서 이를 제거하려면 해당 최대값을 곱합니다.
in the previous O. And then we subtract by the true maximum, because we need to divide everything
이전 O에서. 그런 다음 모든 것을 나누어야 하기 때문에 실제 최대값을 뺍니다.
by the by basically e to the negative mi prime. And then we do the same thing for our current
기본적으로 e를 음수 mi 소수로 변환합니다. 그런 다음 현재에 대해서도 동일한 작업을 수행합니다.
current one. We want to multiply it by whatever it currently is divided, divided by the global
현재 것. 우리는 현재 나누어진 값, 즉 전역 변수로 나누어진 값을 곱하고 싶습니다.
maximum. And then what we want to write to to the O I is basically we want to have our original O I.
최고. 그리고 우리가 OI에 쓰고 싶은 것은 기본적으로 원래의 O I를 갖고 싶다는 것입니다.
So we already computed this, we already computed this. Now we're somewhere here.
그래서 우리는 이미 이것을 계산했습니다. 우리는 이것을 이미 계산했습니다. 이제 우리는 여기 어딘가에 있습니다.
We want to normalize it, we want to multiply by L L I, because we divided by that a lot before.
우리는 그것을 정규화하고 LLI로 곱하고 싶습니다. 왜냐하면 우리는 이전에 LLI로 많이 나누었기 때문입니다.
And we divided by the global softmax softmax true softmax. And, and yeah, we do the same thing
그리고 우리는 글로벌 소프트맥스 소프트맥스 트루 소프트맥스로 나눴습니다. 그리고, 그래, 우리도 같은 일을 해
on our third one here. That's that's this term. And this is basically these terms that was already
여기 세 번째. 바로 이 용어입니다. 그리고 이것은 기본적으로 이미 사용된 용어입니다.
written. And and we rinse and repeat and then we compute the entire thing. So yeah, hopefully
쓴. 그리고 우리는 헹구고 반복한 다음 전체를 계산합니다. 그렇죠, 바랍니다.
that was clear enough. So flash attention guarantees. So it requires of an additional memory,
그것은 충분히 분명했습니다. 그래서 플래시 주의가 보장됩니다. 따라서 추가 메모리가 필요합니다.
which comes from L and M. So, but of course, it requires way fewer HBM accesses, because basically
이는 L과 M에서 비롯됩니다. 물론 기본적으로 HBM 액세스가 훨씬 적게 필요합니다.
we already do all the intermediate steps, we're basically do on the chip, and then we basically
우리는 이미 모든 중간 단계를 수행하고 기본적으로 칩에서 수행한 다음 기본적으로
do one final write at the end. Yeah, these are on the chip, right? So, so yeah, and they prove
마지막에 마지막 쓰기를 하나 하세요. 응, 이것들은 칩에 있지, 그렇지? 그래서, 그렇습니다, 그리고 그들은 증명합니다
some theorem that says in terms of memory access complexity, there's nothing better under some
메모리 액세스 복잡성 측면에서 일부 정리에서는 더 나은 것이 없다는 정리입니다.
mild assumptions. And the next thing is blocks bars flash attention, it's basically an addition to
가벼운 가정. 다음은 블록 바에 주의가 집중되는 것입니다. 기본적으로 추가 기능입니다.
this. So in blocks bars attention, basically, in this, this matrix here, basically, we say, oh, for
이것. 그래서 블록 바에서는 주의를 기울이세요. 기본적으로, 여기 이 매트릭스에서, 기본적으로 우리는 이렇게 말합니다.
these, we only care about like, for example, like the center ones. And for these, like, we don't
이것들은 예를 들어 중앙의 것들에만 관심이 있습니다. 그리고 이것들에 대해서는 우리는 그렇지 않습니다
really care about them, because they're too far apart. And that's very easy to do, you know, just
너무 멀리 떨어져 있기 때문에 정말로 그들을 걱정합니다. 그리고 그건 아주 쉬운 일이죠.
chop this QKT into into blocks. And set this to zero, set this to zero, set this to zero. And
이 QKT를 블록으로 자릅니다. 그리고 이것을 0으로 설정하고, 이것을 0으로 설정하고, 이것을 0으로 설정하세요. 그리고
during the for loop, you know, just skip it. Just do a continue statement in that for loop.
for 루프 중에는 그냥 건너뛰면 됩니다. 해당 for 루프에서 continue 문을 수행하세요.
And you won't assign anything to it. So, yeah, then in terms of its results, yeah, you know,
그리고 당신은 그것에 아무것도 할당하지 않을 것입니다. 네, 그럼 결과를 보면, 네, 아시다시피
it's a it's it's much faster than before. And yeah, again, the performance is should be the
그것은 이전보다 훨씬 빨라진 것입니다. 그리고 네, 다시 말씀드리지만, 성능은 다음과 같아야 합니다.
exact same, because we're not really changing anything. Anything inherent to the model or
우리는 실제로 아무것도 바꾸지 않기 때문에 똑같습니다. 모델에 내재된 모든 것 또는
model training, where all we're doing is changing the way that we read them right on numbers.
모델 훈련에서 우리가 하고 있는 일은 숫자를 읽는 방식을 바꾸는 것뿐입니다.
And again, here shows the speed up. Here's the training time.
그리고 다시, 속도 향상을 보여줍니다. 다음은 훈련 시간입니다.
And as you can see, does a lot faster. It's, you know, it's a lot faster than before.
보시다시피 훨씬 더 빠릅니다. 아시다시피 이전보다 속도가 훨씬 빨라졌습니다.
Ford only covered the Ford pass, there's actually additional backward pass.
포드는 포드 패스만 커버했고, 실제로는 추가적인 백워드 패스도 있었습니다.
You can you can check it out in the appendix of the flash attention paper.
플래시 어텐션 페이퍼 부록에서 확인하실 수 있습니다.
So, yeah, so flash attention is the black one.
네, 그래서 순간적인 관심은 검은 것입니다.
Block sparse flash attention, of course, the fastest. And then, and then it's the green one,
희소한 플래시 주의를 차단하는 것은 물론 가장 빠른 속도입니다. 그리고 그 다음은 녹색입니다.
and then it's flash attention. Actually, Lin former beats it sometimes. But it's kind of cheating,
그리고 그것은 순간적인 관심입니다. 사실 린 전이 가끔 이기기도 해요. 하지만 그건 일종의 속임수죠.
because, you know, flash attention is still of n squared, you're still storing, you're still
왜냐하면, 플래시 어텐션은 여전히 ​​n 제곱이기 때문입니다. 여러분은 여전히 ​​저장하고 있고, 여전히
storing the entire QKT matrix, whereas Lin former, I think, is only storing something linear,
전체 QKT 행렬을 저장하는 반면 Lin 전자는 선형적인 것만 저장하는 것 같습니다.
or the or the computation is is linear.
또는 계산은 선형입니다.
Okay, so flash attention actually also achieves in particular some some some pretty amazing results
좋아요, 그래서 순간적인 관심은 실제로 꽤 놀라운 결과를 얻습니다.
on path x. So what it does is it achieves non random performance on path x,
경로 x에서. 그래서 그것이 하는 일은 경로 x에서 무작위가 아닌 성능을 달성하는 것입니다.
where where it is the first transformer to achieve. She achieved this non random. Sorry.
달성할 첫 번째 변압기인 곳입니다. 그녀는 이것을 무작위가 아닌 달성했습니다. 죄송합니다.
So flash attention is also the first to achieve non random performance. It is the first transformer
따라서 플래시 어텐션은 비랜덤 성능을 가장 먼저 달성하는 것이기도 합니다. 최초의 트랜스포머다.
to achieve non random performance on path x with 16 k context. And flash attention with
16k 컨텍스트를 사용하여 경로 x에서 무작위가 아닌 성능을 달성합니다. 그리고 주의를 집중시키세요
block sparse attention is the first sequence to sequence model to achieve non random performance
Block Sparse Attention은 무작위가 아닌 성능을 달성하기 위한 최초의 시퀀스 대 시퀀스 모델입니다.
on 16 64 k context. Now let me talk about flash attention version two.
16 64k 컨텍스트에서. 이제 Flash Attention 버전 2에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
So there's a few improvements over the existing one. So if you recall from before, instead of
그래서 기존에 비해 몇 가지 개선된 점이 있습니다. 따라서 이전 내용을 기억해 보면
instead of dividing,
나누는 대신,
remember how we basically loaded this and loaded this and then loaded this computed it
기본적으로 이것을 로드하고 로드한 다음 이를 로드하여 계산한 방법을 기억하세요.
computed it. And then we computed this. And then, but back here we divided by some l.
그것을 계산했다. 그리고 우리는 이것을 계산했습니다. 그리고 여기 다시 우리는 l로 나눴습니다.
And then, and then here we multiplied that l back and divided by l prime, which is the sum of
그리고 나서 여기서 우리는 l을 다시 곱하고 l 소수로 나눕니다. 이는 다음의 합입니다.
everything. Basically, it's saying that we don't need to do that. We just don't divide by l in
모든 것. 기본적으로는 그렇게 할 필요가 없다는 뜻입니다. 우리는 l로 나누지 않습니다.
the first place and wait till the end to divide by this big L. And so yeah, so that's that's the idea
첫 번째 장소를 선택하고 끝까지 기다려 이 큰 L로 나누세요. 그래서 예, 그게 아이디어입니다.
here. So that reduces some non matrix multiplication flops, which are usually slower to compute.
여기. 따라서 일반적으로 계산 속도가 느린 일부 비행렬 곱셈 플롭이 줄어듭니다.
And also, another thing is that when we're doing causal masking language modeling,
그리고 또 다른 점은 인과 마스킹 언어 모델링을 할 때
if we're going to mask, this is this is the q, this is the q k t matrix. And if we're going to
마스크를 적용한다면 이것이 q이고 이것이 qkt 행렬입니다. 그리고 만약 우리가 하려고 한다면
mask this part anyways, you know, we never had to compute in the first place and we just escape
어쨌든 이 부분을 가리세요. 우리는 애초에 계산할 필요가 없었고 그냥 탈출했습니다.
it during our for loop. And another thing that flash attention v2 does for us is parallelism.
for 루프 동안에 말이죠. 그리고 Flash Attention v2가 우리에게 제공하는 또 다른 기능은 병렬성입니다.
So in v2, rather than we recall that this was in the k and v were in the inner loop in flash
따라서 v2에서는 이것이 k에 있었고 v가 플래시의 내부 루프에 있었다는 것을 기억하는 대신
attention. In v2, we keep it on the outer loop. We keep it on the outer loop because
주목. v2에서는 외부 루프에 유지합니다. 우리는 그것을 외부 루프에 유지합니다. 왜냐하면
so considered like let's look at this diagram here, consider this basically the square to be
여기 이 다이어그램을 보도록 하겠습니다. 기본적으로 정사각형을 고려하세요.
q k t. And if we parallelize across q, what does that mean? That means we have one worker
qkt. 그리고 우리가 q에 걸쳐 병렬화한다면, 그것은 무엇을 의미합니까? 즉, 직원이 한 명 있다는 뜻입니다.
starting here, and then going this way. Recall that before was like, if we was like going this
여기서 시작해서 이쪽으로 가세요. 전에는 그랬었다는 걸 기억해, 만약 우리가 이렇게 가고 있었다면
way and this way, where we like, we like computed. Okay, it's fun, where we compute it like this
이런 식으로, 우리가 좋아하는 곳에서는 계산된 것을 좋아합니다. 좋아요, 재미있습니다. 이렇게 계산하면 됩니다.
first and then this and this and this and this and this, etc. Now, now what we do is we we
먼저, 다음은 이것, 이것, 이것, 이것, 이것 등등. 자, 이제 우리가 할 일은 우리입니다.
parallelize this way. So when workers, one is on this, it can immediately go to the backward
이런 식으로 병렬화하세요. 그래서 작업자가 이 작업을 수행하면 즉시 뒤로 이동할 수 있습니다.
pass on this. And by the time it gets to the second backward pass, worker two has also done this.
이것을 전달하십시오. 그리고 두 번째 역방향 패스에 도달할 때 작업자 2도 이 작업을 수행했습니다.
So then these five workers here, you can see I'll end up doing six tasks, and they're all able to
그러면 여기 있는 이 5명의 작업자는 제가 6가지 작업을 수행하게 되고 모두가 할 수 있는 작업을 수행하는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
do it. It's possible to do it in a sequential manner because the way we arrange it. And so
해. 우리가 배열하는 방식이기 때문에 순차적으로 하는 것이 가능합니다. 그래서
so that's the way we parallelize it. Another feature that flash attention v2 offers is warp
이것이 바로 우리가 병렬화하는 방식입니다. Flash Attention v2가 제공하는 또 다른 기능은 워프입니다.
partitioning. So within each thread block, there are different threads. And what we want to do is
파티셔닝. 따라서 각 스레드 블록에는 서로 다른 스레드가 있습니다. 그리고 우리가 하고 싶은 일은
we want to split across these threads across q rather than across k. And the reason we want to do
우리는 k가 아닌 q를 통해 이러한 스레드를 분할하고 싶습니다. 그리고 우리가 하고 싶은 이유는
that is because when we split across q with each thread splits across q, then you know, completing
그 이유는 우리가 q를 통해 분할할 때 각 스레드가 q를 통해 분할되면 알다시피 완료되기 때문입니다.
this means that the cross the threads don't have to come communicate with each other. But if we
이는 스레드가 교차하여 서로 통신할 필요가 없음을 의미합니다. 하지만 만약 우리가
split across k, you know, if we come to this and compute this, then we still have to add them
k로 나눠서 계산하면 여전히 더해야 합니다.
together. Whereas this because you know, everything's already added together for you. And it's like
함께. 반면에 이것은 당신이 알고 있기 때문에 모든 것이 이미 당신을 위해 추가되었습니다. 그리고 그것은 마치
row wise, we don't have to do the additional communication cost. And in terms of results,
행 현명한, 우리는 추가 통신 비용을 지불할 필요가 없습니다. 그리고 결과를 보면,
on the left hand side, we have the forward speed and the right hand hand side, we have the backward
왼쪽에는 전진 속도가 있고 오른쪽에는 후진 속도가 있습니다.
speed. And as you can see, purple is the flash attention to and it's much faster than any other
속도. 그리고 보시다시피 보라색은 플래시로 주목을 받고 있으며 다른 것보다 훨씬 빠릅니다.
existing method. And so yeah, that's here's the references. And thank you.
기존 방식. 그리고 그렇습니다. 여기에 참고 자료가 있습니다. 그리고 감사합니다.